[Music]
one of the most common reversible causes
of hearing loss is ear wax buildup ear
wax is normal and if it isn't causing
symptoms should be left alone it doesn't
start interfering with hearing Acuity
until it clogs off at least 80% of the
ear canal ironically hearing aids are a
risk factor for excessive ear wax as are
anything else you put in your ear like
earplugs since that stimulates the ear
wax glands for further irony so make
cotton tipped swabs that as many as
two-thirds of people use to clean their
ears you may think you're making things
better by swabbing out your ears but you
may actually be making them worse simply
removing protective wax can leave your
ear canals dry itchy and achy or even
lead to Q-tip otalgia a term coin to
refer to an ear pain syndrome caused by
cotton tip swabs you shouldn't need to
clean your ear canals at all because the
wax should make its way out on its own
that's right ears are
selfcleaning the lining of your ear
canal grows outward from your eardrum so
secreted ear wax and any dirt that's
trapped is eventually conveyor belted
out of the ear however the self cleaning
mechanism can fail and one in 20 younger
adult and as many as one in three older
adults and lead to excessive or impacted
ear wax
accumulation though they may not even
know it 70% of those surveyed who had
both ears completely blocked with wax
thought their hearing was good but when
their ears were clear they were suddenly
able to hear better clearing out
impacted wax can also improve symptoms
of ear irritation pressure and fullness
so what's the best way to do it Q-tips
are un no no pushing anything into the
ear canal can end up making things worse
by impacting wax even deeper into the
ear or traumatizing the canal resulting
in abrasions
infections or even rarely eardrum
perforation there's even a case report
of a cotton swab causing a brain abscess
and fatal
menitis though the presence of wood
splinters suggests the typic broken off
inside the ear cotton swab packaging
already cautions users against ear canal
insertion but perhaps warning labels
should be made even clearer wrote one
clinical medical officer do not go near
the earhole or avoid the ear
altogether what about those eardrops
sold for wax removal there about a dozen
different marketed formulations on the
market uh none of which appears to work
any better than any other or even
compared to saline which is just salt
water or plain tap water but 5 days of
treatment does clear ear wax in about
one in five cases compared to only one
in 20 that clear up on their own within
that time at the very least those
eardrops may be able to soften wax
before bulb syringe
irrigation irrigation also called ear
syringing involves flushing out the wax
with a low press jet of warm body
temperature water it works up to 70 to
90% of the time and if it doesn't
clinicians have fancy devices to
manually remove the wax under direct
observation uh the irrigation can be
tried at home though researchers
randomized to use a bulb at home at
about a 50% success rate in clearing
their obstruction and armed with this
knowledge were significantly less likely
to subsequently require in-office
irrigation significant complications
only happen in approximately one in a
thousand irrigations you you should not
use an oral water jet there are papers
with names like catastrophic
oalican now even at 1/3 Power Water
picks were shown to be able to perforate
the eard drums of fresh
cavers those who insist on violating
this advice should in the very least use
the lowest setting use a tip with
multiple orifices and make sure the
water stream is directed only against
the walls of the ear canal never
straight back towards the eardrum but
really just don't do it
[Music]